<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Scenario Overview | Eclipse MOSAIC – A Multi-Domain and Multi-Scale Simulation Framework for Connected and Automated Mobility</title>
    <link>https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/docs/scenarios/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/docs/scenarios/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Scenario Overview</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/images/logo.svg</url>
      <title>Scenario Overview</title>
      <link>https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/docs/scenarios/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scenario-Convert Tool</title>
      <link>https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/docs/scenarios/scenario_convert/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/docs/scenarios/scenario_convert/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario-Convert&lt;/strong&gt; does not belong to the open-source part of Eclipse MOSAIC and must be obtained separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, you can use Scenario-Convert &lt;strong&gt;for free&lt;/strong&gt; to generate scenarios which are executable with Eclipse MOSAIC. &lt;strong&gt;




&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dcaiti.tu-berlin.de/research/simulation/download/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Get it here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-info&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The command line interface of &lt;strong&gt;Scenario-Convert&lt;/strong&gt; received a major update with MOSAIC 25.1.
Please follow the &lt;code&gt;--help&lt;/code&gt; command, or use this page to learn how to use the new CLI.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


    

&lt;a class=&#34;mosaic-btn mosaic-btn-primary&#34; href=&#34;https://www.dcaiti.tu-berlin.de/research/simulation/download/&#34; title=&#34;Download scenario-convert from DCAITI mirror&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-download&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;Download scenario-convert from DCAITI mirror&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download the &lt;code&gt;scenario-convert-25.2.zip/tar.gz&lt;/code&gt; bundle from the mirror above.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extract the package to an arbitrary path. It is recommended to extract the package in the very same directory as
MOSAIC (&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;mosaic-root&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the call &lt;code&gt;scenario-convert.bat/sh&lt;/code&gt; on the command line to execute the tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;usage-of-scenario-convert&#34;&gt;Usage of scenario-convert&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/tutorials/create_new_scenario/&#34;&gt;Create a new Scenario Tutorial&lt;/a&gt; provides a detailed introduction to the scenario-convert tool.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario-Convert&lt;/strong&gt; is a tool for generating and modifying MOSAIC scenarios.
In the following we first explain its operation commands and general
arguments.
Secondly, we list various use cases of creating or altering scenarios, supported by several examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a full list of commands and arguments, please follow the &lt;code&gt;--help&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;operation-commands&#34;&gt;Operation Commands&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scenario-Convert offers various commands, which are followed by various additional arguments and parameters to solve specific use-cases to prepare
your MOSAIC scenario. The use-cases are described further below. The following commands exist:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;width:110pt&#34;&gt;Command&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;scenario create&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Creates directory structure for a MOSAIC scenario based on an OSM file, a SUMO scenario, or an existing scenario database.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;database create&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Creates a scenario database based on an OSM file or a SUMO network file.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;database import&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Adds additional information to the scenario database, such as elevation data or buildings, or replaces the road network from a SUMO network file.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;database export&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exports the scenario database to a SUMO network file or GeoJSON files.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;database update&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Updates the database schema of an existing scenario database from an old version to the current version.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;route generate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Generates route(s) from one point to another.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;route import&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Imports routes from a SUMO route file to an existing scenario database.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;route export&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exports routes from the scenario database to a SUMO route file or GeoJSON file.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;route list&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lists all routes which are stored in the scenario database.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;route clear&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Removes all routes from the scenario database.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;mapping create&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Creates a mapping configuration based on the given SUMO route file.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;mapping export&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exports vehicle types and spawners from a given mapping file to a SUMO route file.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;regions create&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Creates a regions configuration for the MOSAIC Cell simulator based on GeoJSON.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;regions configure&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Re-configure network properties of a MOSAIC Cell configuration.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;regions export&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Exports a MOSAIC Cell regions configuration to a GeoJSON file.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-hints&#34;&gt;General Hints&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each command usually requires an argument which points to a file.
This file serves as the input for the command and the supported file type depends on the command.
Some commands support multiple file types, which are internally identified by their filename extensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tool provides a help command (&lt;code&gt;-h&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;--help&lt;/code&gt;) which can be used to generate a general help screen,
(&lt;code&gt;scenario-convert.bat --help&lt;/code&gt;), or specifically for a command (e.g., &lt;code&gt;scenario-convert database create --help&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-case-overview&#34;&gt;Use case overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following, we explain the usage of Scenario-convert in the context of typical use-cases when it comes to scenario creation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;▶️ 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/scenarios/scenario_convert/#-create-mosaic-scenario-from-osm-file&#34;&gt;Create MOSAIC scenario from OSM file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;▶️ 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/scenarios/scenario_convert/#-create-mosaic-scenario-from-sumo-file&#34;&gt;Create MOSAIC scenario from SUMO file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;▶️ 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/scenarios/scenario_convert/#-createimport-routes-for-existing-mosaic-scenario&#34;&gt;Create/Import routes for existing MOSAIC scenario&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;▶️ 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/scenarios/scenario_convert/#-import-height-information-to-existing-mosaic-scenario&#34;&gt;Import height information to existing MOSAIC scenario&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;▶️ 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/scenarios/scenario_convert/#-export-database-or-routes-to-geojson-files&#34;&gt;Export database or routes to GeoJson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;▶️ 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/scenarios/scenario_convert/#-create-mosaic-cell-regions-configuration-from-geojson&#34;&gt;Create and Export MOSAIC Cell Region Configurations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-create-mosaic-scenario-from-osm-file&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;▶️ Create MOSAIC scenario from OSM file&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two ways to create a MOSAIC scenario from an OSM file using scenario-convert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Using a single call with &lt;code&gt;scenario create&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest method to create a MOSAIC scenario from OSM data is to use scenario-convert with the command &lt;code&gt;scenario create&lt;/code&gt;.
One only needs to specify the path to the input OSM file.
The OSM file will first be used to create a scenario database containing road network information.
Afterward, the MOSAIC scenario folder structure and SUMO connection, edge, network, node, route, and config files are created.
You can also use additional arguments alongside this, for example &lt;code&gt;--generate-routes&lt;/code&gt;.
With this argument, routes are generated randomly and added to the scenario database before the scenario is exported to MOSAIC scenario files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The call for the described example would look like this: &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat scenario create &amp;quot;/path/to/map.osm&amp;quot; --generate-routes 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Using two separate calls with the option &lt;code&gt;database create&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;scenario create&lt;/code&gt; subsequently:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works very similarly to the first approach, but gives you more control with handling the database-file.
The first call creates the database from the OSM file.
As a result, there is just the database file that contains all relevant road network information.
It is possible to now alter the database, for example by generating routes or including elevation information.
How to do both of these is described below.
After all changes to the database are completed, you can now call scenario-convert a second time using the second argument and create a
complete MOSAIC scenario structure and SUMO connection, edge, network, node, route, and config files from the database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example calls for this approach would look like this: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;First call:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat database create &amp;quot;/path/to/map.osm&amp;quot; -s &amp;quot;myScenario&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will create a &lt;code&gt;myScenario.db&lt;/code&gt; file in the same directory of the input file &lt;code&gt;map.osm&lt;/code&gt;.
The &lt;code&gt;-s&lt;/code&gt; argument here is optional. If not specified, the database will be named the same as the OSM file. &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second call:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat scenario create &amp;quot;/path/to/myScenario.db&amp;quot; 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional arguments usable with &lt;code&gt;database create&lt;/code&gt; argument when importing OSM files&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Argument&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Explanation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;--skip-buildings&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Skips the import of building information into the database&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;--skip-graph-cleanup&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Turns off the removal of unconnected parts from the main traffic network graph . Since several components of MOSAIC require one main graph without disconnected ways and nodes, this option should be used only if the cleanup procedure is faulty&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;--skip-reduce-ways&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Skips automatic removal of irrelevant ways of the OSM file&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;--skip-turn-restrictions&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ignore all defined turn restrictions on OSM import&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-s / --scenario-name &amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Name to be used for generating the database file.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-create-mosaic-scenario-from-an-existing-sumo-scenario&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;▶️ Create MOSAIC scenario from an existing SUMO scenario&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to convert an already existing SUMO scenario to a usable MOSAIC scenario, you can do that in a similar manner using the following command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using a single call with &lt;code&gt;scenario create&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of this is the same as for creating a MOSAIC scenario from an OSM file.
Simply specify the path to the &lt;code&gt;*.sumocfg&lt;/code&gt; file of your existing SUMO scenario.
Scenario-convert will then wrap the existing SUMO scenario in a MOSAIC scenario by moving SUMO files to the &lt;code&gt;sumo&lt;/code&gt; directory of the resulting MOSAIC scenario.
Furthermore, all other relevant MOSAIC files are created and the projection information is stored in the &lt;code&gt;scenario_config.json&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This example&amp;rsquo;s call would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat scenario create &amp;quot;/path/to/sumo.sumocfg&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the provided scenario has no projection information stored in its network file, then the parameter &lt;code&gt;--import-zone&lt;/code&gt; is required.
The value of this option defines the UTM zone your scenario lies in, e.g., &lt;code&gt;33u&lt;/code&gt; for the east of Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional Arguments with &lt;code&gt;scenario create&lt;/code&gt; when importing SUMO scenario:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Argument&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Explanation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-i / --import-zone &amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;UTM zone of location for projecting coords in default format (e.g. 33u)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;-s / --scenario-name &amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Specifies the name of the scenario. If not given, the base name of the input file is chosen.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-createimport-routes-for-existing-mosaic-scenario&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;▶️ Create/Import routes for existing MOSAIC scenario&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often you have an existing database representing your road network but no routes for vehicles yet.
Routes can be either created from scratch or imported from SUMO route files using scenario-convert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Import a SUMO route file into a database:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importing a route file is possible with just a single call of scenario-convert.
This call reads the routes in the file, saves each route&amp;rsquo;s id and edges, and creates objects in the database for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat route import &amp;quot;/path/to/database.db&amp;quot; &amp;quot;/path/to/routefile.rou.xml&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Creating new routes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating new routes with scenario-convert can be done in two ways. Either by creating random routes through the network using only
&lt;code&gt;--generate-routes&lt;/code&gt; or by additionally specifying start and end point of the route you want to create. Random routes are always created
based on road end points in your network, meaning they always range from one edge of the map to another or from dead end to dead end.
You can also specify start and end point of a route, either in geo coordinates or through node IDs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following examples showcase multiple approaches to generating routes using scenario-convert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generate X random end-to-end routes using &lt;code&gt;-g / --generate-routes&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to generate many routes fast, this option is a good possibility to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat route generate &amp;quot;/path/to/database.db&amp;quot; --max 2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can cap the number of routes generated by passing the argument &lt;code&gt;--max X&lt;/code&gt;, where X is a positive integer.
Scenario-convert then generates a maximum of X routes for each origin/destination pair.
Per default, only 1 route is calculated for each origin/destination pair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculate a single route from point A to point B:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the example above, if a start and end point is given, scenario-convert only calculates a single route between these points
if &lt;code&gt;--max&lt;/code&gt; is not given.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat route generate &amp;quot;/path/to/database.db&amp;quot; --from 52.526371,13.314075 --to 52.512879,13.320099
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The points can be given in geo coordinates or as node IDs.
If given in geo coordinates, make sure the coordinates are within the area of your scenario network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculate X alternative routes from point A to point B:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If start and end point are given and &lt;code&gt;--max X&lt;/code&gt; is passed, where X is a positive integer, scenario-convert calculates
multiple routes between the points, with a maximum of X alternatives. It is not guaranteed that X routes are calculated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat route generate &amp;quot;/path/to/database.db&amp;quot; --from 52.526371,13.314075 --to 52.512879,13.320099 --max 4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. View all routes in a database:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have already created routes and want to view them without using external tools, you can use the argument &lt;code&gt;--list-routes&lt;/code&gt;.
In combination with &lt;code&gt;-d&lt;/code&gt; to set the path to the database you want to view, this outputs a summary of all routes in the database consisting
of route ID, start node ID, end node ID, and route length in meter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;View routes in a database by using the following call:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat route list &amp;quot;/path/to/database.db&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove all routes in a database by using the following call:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat route clear &amp;quot;/path/to/database.db&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-import-height-information-to-existing-mosaic-scenario&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;▶️ Import height information to existing MOSAIC scenario&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importing height information into the database can be done with the command &lt;code&gt;database import&lt;/code&gt; along with the &lt;code&gt;--elevation&lt;/code&gt; option.
It optionally accepts an SRTM file, whose elevation data is then written to the nodes of an existing database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An example call would look like this:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat database import &amp;quot;/path/to/database.db&amp;quot; --elevation &amp;quot;/path/to/srtm.geotiff&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no path to an elevation file is given, elevation data is downloaded from a server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat database import &amp;quot;/path/to/database.db&amp;quot; --elevation
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-export-database-or-routes-to-geojson-files&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;▶️ Export database or routes to GeoJSON files&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you might want to export the contents of your database into a GeoJSON format. For example for visualizations of your road network
using QGIS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use this scenario convert call for this purpose:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat database export &amp;quot;/path/to/database.db&amp;quot; --geojson
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will export the database content into several .geojson files with the same name as the database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat route export &amp;quot;/path/to/database.db&amp;quot; --geojson
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will additionally export all routes into a .geojson file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-create-mosaic-cell-regions-configuration-from-geojson&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;▶️ Create MOSAIC Cell Regions Configuration from GeoJSON&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MOSAIC Cell Simulator requires a configuration file which contains locations, areas, and network properties of individual cell regions.
This file can be hard to write manually, therefore, Scenario Convert some helper methods.
One of these, allows to create a regions configuration from polygons defined in a GeoJSON file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a Cell regions configuration with the help of GeoJSON:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a start, you can use 




&lt;a href=&#34;https://geojson.io/#map=11.66/52.493/13.4134&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;geojson.io&lt;/a&gt; to create several polygons using a map, which would serve as the cellular regions.
Once finished, you can save and download the result as a GeoJSON file.
With Scenario Convert, you can use the following command to create a regions configuration based on the generated GeoJSON file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat regions create &amp;quot;/path/to/regions.geojson&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will generate a &lt;code&gt;regions.json&lt;/code&gt; in the same directory as the input file, which can be loaded as a regions configuration for the MOSAIC Cell Simulator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjust the network properties for all Cell regions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous call, the network properties for each region are filled with default values.
You can adjust these properties by hand, or use Scenario Convert to change certain properties for all regions in one single step:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat regions configure &amp;quot;/path/to/regions.json&amp;quot; -f --set-random-delay 30ms --delay-min 5ms --set-uplink-capacity 100Mbps --set-downlink-capacity 1Gbps --set-packet-loss 0.01
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This call does various changes to the Regions configuration for each region:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sets the delay for all communication links to a random gamma delay with an expected delay of 30 milliseconds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sets the total maximum capacity of the cell region for the uplink to 100Mb per second, and for the downlink to 1Gb per second.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sets the packet loss probability for all communication attempts to 1%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Export the cell regions file for visualization or editing to GeoJSON:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, you can use Scenario Convert to export an existing Cell regions configuration to a GeoJSON file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat regions export &amp;quot;/path/to/regions.json&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will generate a &lt;code&gt;regions.geojson&lt;/code&gt; in the same directory as the input file.
All network properties are appended to the properties section of each GeoJSON feature.
Therefore, after altering the file, you can import the file again to recreate the Cell regions configuration file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;scenario-convert.bat regions create &amp;quot;/path/to/regions.geojson&amp;quot; -f
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Additional Scenario Configuration</title>
      <link>https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/docs/scenarios/scenario_configuration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/docs/scenarios/scenario_configuration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This page aims to give you a brief overview of additional simulators and visualizers that can be used with Eclipse MOSAIC. For this the Steglitz scenario from 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/tutorials/create_new_scenario/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Create a new Scenario&amp;rdquo;-Tutorial&lt;/a&gt; is being used. For more detailed explanations of the configurations have a
look at 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/scenarios/&#34;&gt;the overview&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
If you already played with the 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/tutorials/barnim_simulation_basics/&#34;&gt;Barnim&lt;/a&gt;-tutorial, you probably noticed that it contains far
more folders in the scenario structure compared to the Steglitz example. Those additional directories contain
configurations for various simulators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-plaintext&#34;&gt;└─ Barnim
   ├─ application
   ├─ cell
   ├─ environment
   ├─ mapping
   ├─ ns3
   ├─ output
   ├─ sns
   ├─ sumo
   └─ scenario_config.json .................. General configuration of the simulation scenario
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;let-the-cars-loose&#34;&gt;Let the cars loose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a starting point we&amp;rsquo;ll look at the scenario that we created using this command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;scenario-convert.sh --osm2mosaic -i steglitz.osm --generate-routes
--route-begin-latlon 52.4551693,13.3193474 --route-end-latlon 52.4643101,13.3206834 --max-number-of-routes 3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll end up with a folder looking like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-plaintext&#34;&gt;└─ steglitz
   ├─ application
   |  └─ steglitz.db
   ├─ mapping
   |  └─ mapping_config.json
   ├─ sumo
   |  ├─ steglitz.net.xml
   |  └─ steglitz.sumocfg
   └─ scenario_config.json .................. General configuration of the simulation scenario
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a look in the 





  
  

    

    
    

    
    
      
        
          
            
            
            
          
        
      
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/scenarios/files/steglitz_mapping_config.json&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;mapping_config.json&lt;/a&gt;,
you can see that the scenario-convert script automatically assigns cars to the three routes created. You can use this
file as a blueprint for your own scenario, have a look 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/scenarios/#applications-and-mapping&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
to get more details on possible adaptions.&lt;br&gt;
Below is a short video of the scenario displayed in the SUMO-GUI. We marked the three different routes the cars
follow.&lt;/p&gt;












  


&lt;video controls &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;../images/steglitz_routes.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;communication-simulators-cell-ns3-omnetpp-sns&#34;&gt;Communication Simulators (cell, ns3, omnetpp, sns)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We won&amp;rsquo;t implement any functionality for the steglitz example here but rather have a look at the






  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/tutorials/barnim_simulation_basics/&#34;&gt;Barnim&lt;/a&gt;-tutorial. In the &lt;code&gt;scenario_config.json&lt;/code&gt; of the Barnim scenario you can see where the
communication simulators are activated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;federates&amp;quot;: {
    &amp;quot;cell&amp;quot;: false,
    &amp;quot;omnetpp&amp;quot;: false,
    &amp;quot;ns3&amp;quot;: false,
    &amp;quot;sns&amp;quot;: true
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/tutorials/&#34;&gt;tutorials&lt;/a&gt; and 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/tutorials/additional_examples/&#34;&gt;additional examples&lt;/a&gt; demonstrate use cases for
communication usages and you should have a look at them if you are uncertain where to start. Furthermore we
recommend copying the configuration-files for the simulator you are going to use from the 





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/tutorials/barnim_simulation_basics/&#34;&gt;Barnim scenario&lt;/a&gt;. It
contains the most complete configurations and is well maintained.&lt;br&gt;
If you are an expert with one of the external network simulators (





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/simulators/network_simulator_ns3/&#34;&gt;ns3&lt;/a&gt;,






  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/simulators/network_simulator_omnetpp/&#34;&gt;OMNeT++&lt;/a&gt;) the Barnim scenario will also give
you an overview on how to configure those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-simulators&#34;&gt;Other Simulators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to employ other simulators for the scenario, make sure to have it enabled in the &lt;code&gt;scenario_config.json&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;environment-simulator&#34;&gt;Environment Simulator&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Environment Simulator can be used to emit events to vehicles inside predefined borders. In the Barnim scenario
the Environment Simulator is used to simulate an icy area, which is then noticed by the sensors of equipped vehicles.&lt;br&gt;
Every defined event requires a type, a defined geographical area (e.g. circular, rectangular), the strength and a time frame. Have a look
at the 





  
  

    

    
    

    
    
      
        
          
            
            
            
          
        
      
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/scenarios/files/eventserver_config.json&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;environment_config.json&lt;/a&gt; to see how this can be configured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;battery-simulator&#34;&gt;Battery Simulator&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Battery Simulator allows to simulate discharging and recuperation of electric vehicles, and in connection with the
Charging Station Simulator also re-charging. It offers a lot of customization, as you can
dynamically load your own battery, vehicle and environment models. Have a look a the 





  
  

    

    
    

    
    
      
        
          
            
            
            
          
        
      
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/scenarios/files/battery_config.json&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;battery_config.json&lt;/a&gt;,
taken from the Barnim scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;charging-station-simulator&#34;&gt;Charging Station Simulator&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Charging Station Simulator extends the modeling possibilities of the Battery Simulator for re-charging.
Since Charging Stations are also application units in the Application Simulator, most of the configuration and modeling is
provided by mapping a possible application to the charging station.
Accordingly, the 





  
  

    

    
    

    
    
      
        
          
            
            
            
          
        
      
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/scenarios/files/charging_config.json&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;charging_config.json&lt;/a&gt; covers, with the charging station range, merely one parameter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;output&#34;&gt;Output&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various options to generate output results of your simulations (see the






  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/docs/visualization/filevis/&#34;&gt;Visualization chapter&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step is to create a file called &lt;code&gt;output_config.xml&lt;/code&gt; in a new directory called &lt;code&gt;output&lt;/code&gt;.
If you used the scenario-convert tool the file should be generated automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-plaintext&#34;&gt;└─ steglitz
   ├─ application
   |  └─ steglitz.db
   ├─ mapping
   |  └─ mapping_config.json
   ├─ output
   |  └─ output_config.xml
   ├─ sumo
   |  ├─ steglitz.net.xml
   |  └─ steglitz.sumocfg
   └─ scenario_config.json .................. General configuration of the simulation scenario
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example configuration for output generation can be taken from the example scenarios from the tutorials section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, make sure the visualization federate is activated in the &lt;code&gt;scenario_config.json&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
```xml
&lt;!-- Visualization -- &gt;
&lt;federate id=&#34;output&#34; active=&#34;true&#34;/&gt;
```

Now we have to configure the statistics visualizer itself. This [visualizer_config.xml](/docs/scenarios/files/steglitz_visualizer_config.xml) contains the basic
configuration to calculate the average travel times for the vehicles. If you want to make adaptions, please
refer to [statistics visualizer](/docs/visualization/statistics).  
Go ahead and run the simulation one more time. Afterwards the log-directory should contain a file called 
`AverageVehicleTravelTime.csv` in a directory called `StatisticsVisualizer`:
```csv
group;group-value;total;
Car;186.369;336;
```
This tells us that there was a total amount of 336 vehicles of the type `Car` in the simulation, which traveled
for 186.369  seconds on average.
--&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Run Simulation Series</title>
      <link>https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/docs/scenarios/run_simulation_series/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/docs/scenarios/run_simulation_series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-extended&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;extended-icon&#34; style=&#34;background-image: url(/mosaic/img/alert-extended.svg)&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Simulation Runner&lt;/strong&gt; is part of &lt;strong&gt;





  
  

    

    
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
    

    
  

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eclipse.dev/mosaic/mosaic/download/#overview&#34;&gt;MOSAIC Extended&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
For further information on licenses, feel free to contact us via &lt;strong&gt;





  
  

&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:mosaic@fokus.fraunhofer.de&#34;&gt;mosaic@fokus.fraunhofer.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chapter explains how to efficiently run a simulation series of a scenario using the Simulation Runner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Simulation Runner is a tool for automatic simulation parametrization and execution. It provides a comfortable way to configure the execution of multiple simulations, e.g. of simulation series including several runs where only few parameters are changed in each run. With the Simulation Runner, a simulation series can be defined, for example, where the V2X penetration rate is changed in each simulation run. As a result, all  Eclipse MOSAIC simulation runs are started automatically according to the defined parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;usage&#34;&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Simulation Runner is started as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;./simulation-runner.sh -c /scenarios/&amp;lt;scenario_name&amp;gt;/simrunner_config.xml -u &amp;lt;user-id&amp;gt; -p &amp;lt;number_of_parallel_simulations&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Windows use &lt;code&gt;simulation-runner.bat&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The configuration file &lt;code&gt;/scenarios/&amp;lt;scenario_name&amp;gt;/mosaic/simrunner_config.xml&lt;/code&gt; contains the parameterization information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the option &lt;code&gt;-e&lt;/code&gt; the Eclipse MOSAIC executable can be passed. Passing the Eclipse MOSAIC executable is optional if it is located in the mosaic folder or given in the &lt;code&gt;simrunner_config.xml&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;configuration&#34;&gt;Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following example shows a complete configuration. Using this configuration, the Simulation Runner would try to run a scenario called Barnim while adapting the mapping, the configuration file of SNS, and Eclipse MOSAIC configuration files. The actual simulation is triggered by generating an adapted scenario folder and calling the same executable the user would normally trigger himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-xml&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version=&amp;quot;1.0&amp;quot; encoding=&amp;quot;UTF-8&amp;quot;?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;configuration&amp;gt;

  &amp;lt;!-- basic configuration --&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;mosaic 
      location=&amp;quot;/path/to/mosaic_folder&amp;quot; 
      executable=&amp;quot;mosaic.sh&amp;quot; 
      parallelSimulations=&amp;quot;2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;scenario 
      name=&amp;quot;Barnim&amp;quot; 
      config=&amp;quot;scenarios/Barnim/scenario_config.json&amp;quot; 
      persistent=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; 
      progressLogger=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;!--argument&amp;gt;-o TRACE&amp;lt;/argument--&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;!--argument&amp;gt;-w 0&amp;lt;/argument--&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/scenario&amp;gt;
  
  &amp;lt;!-- define connected values for controlled changes --&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;dimension name=&amp;quot;PenetrationRates&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
     &amp;lt;parameter name=&amp;quot;V2XVehiclePercentage&amp;quot; 
         file=&amp;quot;mapping/mapping_config.json&amp;quot; 
         fileFormat=&amp;quot;json&amp;quot; item=&amp;quot;vehicles[0].types[0].weight&amp;quot; 
         type=&amp;quot;ValueList&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
         &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;0.0&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
         &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;0.5&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
         &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;0.75&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
     &amp;lt;/parameter&amp;gt;
     &amp;lt;parameter name=&amp;quot;ClassicVehiclePercentage&amp;quot; 
         file=&amp;quot;mapping/mapping_config.json&amp;quot; 
         fileFormat=&amp;quot;json&amp;quot; 
         item=&amp;quot;vehicles[0].types[1].weight&amp;quot; type=&amp;quot;ValueList&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
         &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;1&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
         &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;0.5&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
         &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;0.25&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
     &amp;lt;/parameter&amp;gt;
     &amp;lt;parameter name=&amp;quot;Simulationtime&amp;quot; 
         file=&amp;quot;scenario_config.json&amp;quot; 
         fileFormat=&amp;quot;json&amp;quot; 
         item=&amp;quot;simulation.duration&amp;quot;
         type=&amp;quot;ValueList&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
         &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;100&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
         &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;100&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
         &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;100&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
     &amp;lt;/parameter&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/dimension&amp;gt;
  
  &amp;lt;!-- define values for automatically permuted simulations --&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;parameter name=&amp;quot;SinglehopRadius&amp;quot; 
      file=&amp;quot;sns/sns_config.json&amp;quot; 
      fileFormat=&amp;quot;json&amp;quot; 
      item=&amp;quot;singlehopRadius&amp;quot; 
      type=&amp;quot;ValueList&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;500&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;600&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/parameter&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/configuration&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The configuration contains three distinct parts of configuration. The system specific definition, the scenario definition and the parametrization. While the first two parts will be explained as part of this section, the parametrization will be explained in it’s own section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;system-specific-definition&#34;&gt;System Specific Definition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-xml&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;mosaic 
   location=&amp;quot;/path/to/mosaic_folder&amp;quot;
   executable=&amp;quot;mosaic.sh&amp;quot; 
   parallelSimulations=&amp;quot;2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system specific part of the configuration above is the only part of the configuration that can be overwritten using a second configuration file. It contains the following attributes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Attribute&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;location&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Location of the Eclipse MOSAIC installation to use (can be relative or absolute). This attribute can be omitted in case the mosaic executable is in the same location as the simulation-runner executable.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;executable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;The provided executable is used to start the simulation. This value is optional and will automatically be set to the default *.bat or *.sh file when omitted. (relative path to &lt;code&gt;location&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;parallelSimulations&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Defines how many simulations are started in parallel to speed up things. Be aware that you should only use this if you have multiple cores available. This might also coincide with the threads option in the Eclipse MOSAIC configuration. The default is &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;scenario-definition&#34;&gt;Scenario Definition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-xml&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;scenario 
   name=&amp;quot;Barnim&amp;quot; 
   config=&amp;quot;scenarios/Barnim/scenario_config.json&amp;quot; 
   persistent=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot; 
   progressLogger=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;!--argument&amp;gt;-o TRACE&amp;lt;/argument--&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;!--argument&amp;gt;-w 0&amp;lt;/argument--&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/scenario&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scenario definition above contains everything needed to identify the scenario to execute along with parameters that need to be passed to the Eclipse MOSAIC executable. It contains the following attributes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Attribute&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;name&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;The name of the simulation to run. This is expected to be the same as the scenario&amp;rsquo;s folder name and is used to automatically generate the path pointing to the scenario&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;scenario_config.json&lt;/code&gt; in a default case. It can be omitted if the config option is set.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;config&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;This is an optional value containing the concrete path to the scenario&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;scenario_config.json&lt;/code&gt;. This can be used if the scenario is not placed in the default scenarios folder (which is discouraged) and overwrites the path generated by the name attribute. Either name or config have to be defined! (path relative to &lt;code&gt;location&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;persistent&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Defines if the generated files in the Simulation Runner (scenarios with adapted configurations), etc (hohsts.json, logback.xml, runtime.json) and tmp directories will be kept after simulation (value &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;) or deleted (value &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;progressLogger&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Writes summary of Simulation Runner execution to std out (value &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;), default is &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;stdoutLogger&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Writes log messages from the Eclipse MOSAIC executable to stdout when (value &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;), default is &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The configuration can also contain a number of additional arguments that are passed to the executable without any changes, separated by spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;parametrization&#34;&gt;Parametrization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heart of this tool is the parametrization of simulations. Using this, one can define values in the default configuration that are adapted between simulation runs. How many simulation runs are performed is defined by the number of changes configured, enriched with the information about simulation repetitions.
For the example in listing &amp;lsquo;Example Configuration&amp;rsquo; it is expected that the mapping file to be changed has one &lt;code&gt;vehicles&lt;/code&gt; definition spawning multiple cars with a weighted &lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt; distribution defining first the equipped and then the unequipped vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;parameters&#34;&gt;Parameters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-xml&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;parameter name=&amp;quot;V2XVehiclePercentage&amp;quot; file=&amp;quot;mapping/mapping_config.json&amp;quot; fileFormat=&amp;quot;json&amp;quot; item=&amp;quot;vehicles[0].types[0].weight&amp;quot; type=&amp;quot;ValueList&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;0&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;50&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;value&amp;gt;75&amp;lt;/value&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/parameter&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each value that should be changed in a run is defined by a &lt;code&gt;parameter&lt;/code&gt; element identified by a &lt;code&gt;name&lt;/code&gt; (see listing above). The base value is the &lt;code&gt;file&lt;/code&gt; which should be changed (relative to the scenario folder). Currently it is needed to define what &lt;code&gt;fileFormat&lt;/code&gt; is expected from that file, which has impact on the syntax of the item definition which denotes what part of this file should be changed (this will be explained in a bit). The final value is the &lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt; which denotes how the value change behaves. The child elements depend on this definition and will also be explained in a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;fileFormat&lt;/code&gt; can be one of &lt;code&gt;xml&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;json&lt;/code&gt;. The item syntax is as followed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;xml&lt;/code&gt;: contains an XPath expression (but without the root element)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;json&lt;/code&gt;: contains an array-style definition of the target value. The value in the listing above would change line 13 in the listing below. (In the first entry of vehicles the attribute weight of the types first entry).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{
  &amp;quot;prototypes&amp;quot;: [ { &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Car&amp;quot; } ],
  &amp;quot;vehicles&amp;quot;: [
    {
      &amp;quot;startingTime&amp;quot;: 5.0,
      &amp;quot;targetFlow&amp;quot;: 1200,
      &amp;quot;maxNumberVehicles&amp;quot;: 250,
      &amp;quot;route&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;types&amp;quot;: [
        {
          &amp;quot;applications&amp;quot;: [ &amp;quot;org.eclipse.mosaic.app.tutorial.WeatherWarningApp&amp;quot; ],
          &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Car&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;weight&amp;quot;: 0.2
        },
        {
          &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Car&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;weight&amp;quot;: 0.8
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt; can currently only have two entries:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ValueList&lt;/code&gt;: This expects a list of values as child elements of the parameter. Each value will be used for at least one permutation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;IntegerGenerator&lt;/code&gt;: This automatically generates integer values to write as values. The generated numbers can be configured by adding these optional attributes to the parameter element:&lt;br&gt;
– &lt;code&gt;start&lt;/code&gt;: denoting a minimal number where generation should start (this will be the first value), default is &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
– &lt;code&gt;step&lt;/code&gt;: denoting the number that will be added to the previous value to generate the new one, default is &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;end&lt;/code&gt;: denoting the maximum number (exclusive), default is &lt;code&gt;start + 10 * step&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;permutation-of-parameters&#34;&gt;Permutation of parameters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When multiple such parameter elements are defined, a permutation for each specific value definition is generated. Lets say defined are parameters A and B and each parameter has values a and b. The resulting permutations would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;A=a, B=a
A=b, B=a
A=a, B=b
A=b, B=b
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dimensions&#34;&gt;Dimensions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it is wanted to group some value changes. This can be necessary when changed values need to sum up to a specific value or when specific (named) output files need to be defined. This can be done by enclosing the affected &lt;code&gt;parameters&lt;/code&gt; into a &lt;code&gt;dimension&lt;/code&gt; definition. Doing this the values of each &lt;code&gt;parameter&lt;/code&gt; are connected by their index. For this to work the number of values for each parameter have to be the same. The example in listing &amp;lsquo;Example Configuration&amp;rsquo; utilizes this function to make sure the vehicle percentages sum up to 100. The generated permutations for the dimension enclosed parameters are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;V2XVehiclePercentage=0,  ClassicVehiclePercentage=100
V2XVehiclePercentage=50, ClassicVehiclePercentage=50
V2XVehiclePercentage=75, ClassicVehiclePercentage=25
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When additionally parameters are defined which are not enclosed in the &lt;code&gt;dimension&lt;/code&gt; tag or another dimension tag is defined, then the permutations will be extended even further. The full permutation for listing &amp;lsquo;Example Configuration&amp;rsquo; is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;PenetrationRates(V2XVehiclePercentage=0,  ClassicVehiclePercentage=100), SinglehopRadius=500
PenetrationRates(V2XVehiclePercentage=50, ClassicVehiclePercentage=50),  SinglehopRadius=500
PenetrationRates(V2XVehiclePercentage=75, ClassicVehiclePercentage=25),  SinglehopRadius=500
PenetrationRates(V2XVehiclePercentage=0,  ClassicVehiclePercentage=100), SinglehopRadius=600
PenetrationRates(V2XVehiclePercentage=50, ClassicVehiclePercentage=50),  SinglehopRadius=600
PenetrationRates(V2XVehiclePercentage=75, ClassicVehiclePercentage=25),  SinglehopRadius=600
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;additional-information&#34;&gt;Additional Information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some side effects to remember when working with this tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ports:&lt;/strong&gt; The Simulation Runner supports automatic assigning of free ports for federates. This means that all federates configured in the &lt;code&gt;simrunner_config.xml&lt;/code&gt; will get a free port configured by default. This enables multiple simulations to be run simultaneously as long as the federates are started by Eclipse MOSAIC. If some federates are not started through Eclipse MOSAIC but are already running, this will not work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paths:&lt;/strong&gt; Relative paths of the files to be modified will be expanded with the deployment directory of the current simulation run, as defined in the value &lt;code&gt;location&lt;/code&gt;, to an absolute one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adaptations:&lt;/strong&gt; All values will be modified in copies of the original scenario. The copies will be placed in the Simulation Runner folder in the Eclipse MOSAIC base directory and will be (if not deactivated by configuration) deleted upon completion of the simulation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
